A Guide to the Martha Woodrum Zillhardt Papers, 1802-2010
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Martha Woodrum Zillhardt Papers, 1802-2010
The Library of Virginia
51582
37 boxes (17.65 cu. ft)
Martha Woodrum Zillhardt
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Robert H. Woodrum, June 2015.
Biographical Information
Martha Anne Woodrum Zillhardt (1916-2002) was born in Roanoke Virginia to United States Senator Clifton A. Woodrum, Sr. and Martha Hancock Woodrum. In 1936, Martha Woodrum Zillhardt graduated from Gunston Hall School in Washington, D.C. and began managing her father's reelection campaign. Martha Woodrum Zillhardt began worked for the WDBJ Radio Station, during which time she began taking flying lessons, which she initially kept secret from her father, who was an avid supporter of the new aviation industry. In 1940, Martha Woodrum Zillhardt flew her first solo flight and began working as a flight instructor. Soon after, Martha Anne established Woodrum Flying Service, which offered flight instruction, rentals, and charter flights at Roanoke's Woodrum Field, renamed to honor Clifton A. Woodrum Sr.'s contributions to aviation. In 1953, Martha Anne married Jack Zillhardt, and moved to Binghampton, N.Y. In 1963, the couple retired to Fincastle, Virginia. Martha Woodrum Zillhardt was a member of the Roanoke Airport Advisory Committee and was inducted into the Virginia Aviation Hall of Fame in 1985. She was buried in Evergreen Burial Park in Roanoke, Virginia.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1802-2010, of Martha Anne Woodrum Zillhardt (1916-2002) of Roanoke, Virginia, consist of cards, correspondence, ephemera, ledgers, newspaper clippings, newsletters, photographs, programs, scrapbooks, speeches, and other papers detailing Zillhardt's early life, education, and career as a flying instructor. Collection also includes Zillhardt's activities as campaign manager for her father's reelection campaign and her many travels, both nationally and internationally. Also includes papers relating to her father Clifton A. Woodrum (1895-1954), her husband Dr. Jacob Charles Zillhardt (1905-1989), and her cousin Harry P. Hancock (1926-2011).
Contents List
- Account Ledger, undated. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Acorn Yearbook, 1933. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Airport Appreciation Days Programs, 1975-1976. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Amateur Built Aircraft Log Book, 1989. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- American Universal Geography, Volume 1, 1812. (Box 30, Folder 1)
- Aviation Materials, undated. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Aviation Papers, 1952-1958 and undated. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Baby Book of Harry Price Hancock, 1954. (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Beechcraft Certified Service Stations, 1951. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Beechwood, undated. (Box 1, Folder 10)
- CAA Statistical Handbook of Civil Aviation, 1957. (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Calendar, April 1945. (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Calendar, December 1945. (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Calendar, July 1946. (Box 1, Folder 14)
- California Race, 1948-1950. (Box 2, Folder 1)
- California Race, 1950. (Box 2, Folder 2)
- California Trip, February and March 1950. (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Checkbook, 1953-1956. (Box 2, Folder 4)
- "Clifton A. Woodrum of Virginia: A Southern Progressive in Congress" by James E. Sargent, July 1981. (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Congressional Record, 1927-1933. (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Contact Newspaper, 1949. (Box 37, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1908-1917. (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1917. (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1917-1920. (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1943-1949. (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1949-1956. (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1956-1995. (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, undated. (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, undated. (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, undated. (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Correspondence and Bills, 1941-1950. (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Coupons, undated. (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Course and Mile-Gauge Instrument, undated. (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Diary of Martha Woodrum, 1934-1935. (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Encased Photograph, 1908. (Box 31, Folder 2)
- Encased Photograph, 1964. (Box 32, Folder 3)
- Encased Photograph, undated. (Box 32, Folder 1)
- Encased Photograph, undated. (Box 32, Folder 2)
- Encased Photograph, undated. (Box 33, Folder 1)
- Encased Photograph, undated. (Box 33, Folder 2)
- Engine and Reduction Drive Log Book, 1989. (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Ephemera, undated. (Box 4, Folder 8)
- "February Correspondence", 1950. (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Financial Papers, 1954-1964 and undated. (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Forbes Magazine, April 15, 1951. (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Genealogical Papers, 1983. (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Glass Artwork, undated. (Box 31, Folder 4)
- Glass Photograph, undated. (Box 31, Folder 5)
- Glass Photograph, undated. (Box 31, Folder 6)
- Glass Photograph, undated. (Box 31, Folder 7)
- Glass Photograph, undated. (Box 31, Folder 8)
- Glass Plate Negative, undated. (Box 31, Folder 3)
- Gunston Hall Diploma of Martha Woodrum Zillhardt, 1936. (Box 37, Folder 2)
- "The Hammond Genealogy" by Fiske Edward Hammond, 1919. (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Hancock Family History, 2010. (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Hancocks of Virginia, undated. (Box 37, Folder 3)
- Holy Bible, 1802. (Box 30, Folder 2)
- The Hymnal, 1892. (Box 30, Folder 3)
- Illustrations, undated. (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Inside Passage Newspaper, 1976. (Box 37, Folder 4)
- Jenny Lind Newspaper, undated. (Box 37, Folder 5)
- Journal of the Roanoke Historical Society, Winter 1968. (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Kodachrome Slides, undated. (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Master Plan for the Roanoke Municipal Airport, 1969. (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Master Plan for the Roanoke Municipal Airport, 1969. (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Medical Papers, 1959 and 1981. (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Merriam-Webster Pocket Dictionary, 1947. (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Miscellaneous Papers of Martha W. Zillhardt, 1932-1957. (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Miscellaneous Photographs, 1942 and undated. (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Miscellaneous Photographs, 1967, 1986, and undated. (Box 6, Folder 3)
- M/V Sun Princess Menus, 1976. (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Name Cards, undated. (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Name Cards, undated. (Box 6, Folder 6)
- National Aeronautic Association of U.S.A Certificate, 1950. (Box 6, Folder 7)
- National Air Races Programs, 1946-1949. (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Negatives, undated. (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Negatives, undated. (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Negatives, undated. (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Negatives, undated. (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Negatives, undated. (Box 8)
- Negatives, undated. (Box 9)
- Negatives, undated. (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Negatives, undated. (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1922-1949. (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1950-1992. (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Newspaper Clippings, undated. (Box 10, Folder 5)
- New Testament, 1884. (Box 28, Folder 1)
- The Ninety-Nines Membership Directory, 1965-1966. (Box 10, Folder 6)
- Notebook, undated. (Box 10, Folder 7)
- Notebook, undated. (Box 10, Folder 8)
- Notebook, undated. (Box 10, Folder 9)
- Notebook, undated. (Box 10, Folder 10)
- Notebook, undated. (Box 10, Folder 11)
- Notebook, undated. (Box 10, Folder 12)
- Notebook of Martha W. Zillhardt, 1949. (Box 11, Folder 1)
- Notebook of Martha W. Zillhardt, 1950-1951. (Box 11, Folder 2)
- Notes, undated. (Box 11, Folder 3)
- Pamphlets, 1974 and undated. (Box 11, Folder 4)
- Pamphlets, undated. (Box 11, Folder 5)
- Pamphlets- St. Margaret's School for Girls, undated. (Box 11, Folder 6)
- Papers from Account Ledger, undated. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Papers from Checkbook, 1953-1956. (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Papers from Scrapbook (blank), undated. (Box 26, Folder 3)
- Papers from Scrapbook Pages, 1926-1929. (Box 26, Folder 5)
- Papers from Scrapbook Pages, 1926-1929. (Box 26, Folder 6)
- Papers from Scrapbook Pages, 1926-1929. (Box 26, Folder 7)
- Papers of Harry Price Hancock, 1971 and 1972. (Box 11, Folder 7)
- Paperweight with Photograph, 1967. (Box 31, Folder 1)
- Passport of Martha Price Hancock, 1985. (Box 11, Folder 8)
- Photograph Album, 1926-1969. (Box 11, Folder 9)
- Photograph Album, 1926-1969. (Box 12, Folder 1)
- Photograph Album, 1926-1969. (Box 12, Folder 2)
- Photograph Album, 1930. (Box 12, Folder 3)
- Photograph Album, 1951-2008 and undated. (Box 12, Folder 4)
- Photograph Album, 1951-2008 and undated. (Box 12, Folder 5)
- Photograph Album, 1951-2008 and undated. (Box 12, Folder 6)
- Photograph Album, 1951-2008 and undated. (Box 12, Folder 7)
- Photograph Album, 1955-1976. (Box 13, Folder 1)
- Photograph Album, 1955-1976. (Box 13, Folder 2)
- Photograph Album, 1988-1990. (Box 13, Folder 3)
- Photograph Album, 1988-1990. (Box 13, Folder 4)
- Photograph Album, 1991-1994. (Box 13, Folder 5)
- Photograph Album, undated. (Box 13, Folder 6)
- Photograph Album, undated. (Box 13, Folder 7)
- Photograph Album, undated. (Box 14, Folder 1)
- Photograph Album of the Bombing of Cassino, 1944. (Box 14, Folder 2)
- Photographs of Aircrafts, 1925-1950 and undated. (Box 14, Folder 3)
- Photographs of Aircrafts, 1944-1957 and undated. (Box 14, Folder 4)
- Photographs of Aircrafts, 1989-1990 and undated. (Box 14, Folder 5)
- Photographs of Aircrafts, undated. (Box 14, Folder 6)
- Photographs of Aircrafts, undated. (Box 15, Folder 1)
- Photographs of Aircrafts, undated. (Box 15, Folder 2)
- Photographs of Aircrafts, undated. (Box 15, Folder 3)
- Photographs of Aircrafts, undated. (Box 15, Folder 4)
- Photographs of Airplanes, undated. (Box 35, Folder 1)
- Photographs of Animals, 1937-1944. (Box 15, Folder 5)
- Photorgaphs of Animals, undated. (Box 15, Folder 6)
- Photograph of Beechcraft, 1935. (Box 37, Folder 13)
- Photograph of Boy Scouts, undated. (Box 35, Folder 2)
- Photographs of Buildings, 1937-1993 and undated. (Box 15, Folder 7)
- Photographs of Buildings, 1967-1972 and undated. (Box 16, Folder 1)
- Photographs of Buildings, undated. (Box 16, Folder 2)
- Photograph of Clifton A. Woodrum, undated. (Box 37, Folder 10)
- Photograph of Dick Owens and Charles Hofer, undated. (Box 35, Folder 3)
- Photograph of Dr. Richard and Kitty Owens, undated. (Box 35, Folder 4)
- Photographs of Groups, 1942-1994 and undated. (Box 16, Folder 3)
- Photographs of Groups, undated. (Box 35, Folder 5)
- Photographs of Hancock-Price Family, 1891-1951. (Box 16, Folder 4)
- Photographs of Hancock-Price Family, 1951-1977. (Box 16, Folder 5)
- Photographs of Hancock-Price Family, 1952-1993. (Box 16, Folder 6)
- Photographs of Hancock-Price Family, undated. (Box 16, Folder 7)
- Photograph of Harry Price Hancock, undated. (Box 37, Folder 8)
- Photograph of Irving Sharp and Martha Anne, undated. (Box 35, Folder 6)
- Photographs of John Robert Hill, undated. (Box 16, Folder 8)
- Photographs of Landscapes, 1936-1941 and undated. (Box 16, Folder 9)
- Photographs of Landscapes, undated. (Box 17, Folder 1)
- Photographs of Landscapes, 1936-1967 and undated. (Box 17, Folder 2)
- Photographs of Landscapes, undated. (Box 35, Folder 7)
- Photographs of the launching of the S.S. Sanconnet, 1944. (Box 17, Folder 3)
- Photographs of Marinas, 1925-1942. (Box 17, Folder 4)
- Photograph of Martha Woodrum with Flight Students, undated. (Box 35, Folder 9)
- Photographs of Martha W. Zillhardt, 1937-1941. (Box 17, Folder 5)
- Photographs of Martha W. Zillhardt, 1942-1951. (Box 17, Folder 6)
- Photographs of Martha W. Zillhardt, 1948-1950. (Box 18, Folder 1)
- Photographs of Martha W. Zillhardt, 1953 and undated. (Box 18, Folder 2)
- Photographs of Martha W. Zillhardt, undated. (Box 18, Folder 3)
- Photographs of Martha W. Zillhardt, undated. (Box 18, Folder 4)
- Photographs of Martha W. Zillhardt, undated. (Box 18, Folder 5)
- Photographs of Martha W. Zillhardt, undated. (Box 18, Folder 6)
- Photographs of Martha W. Zillhardt, undated. (Box 19, Folder 1)
- Photographs of Martha W. Zillhardt, undated. (Box 19, Folder 2)
- Photographs of Martha W. Zillhardt, undated. (Box 19, Folder 3)
- Photographs of Martha W. Zillhardt, undated. (Box 19, Folder 4)
- Photographs of Martha W. Zillhardt, undated. (Box 19, Folder 5)
- Photographs of Martha Woodrum Zillhardt, undated. (Box 35, Folder 8)
- Photograph of Martha Zillhardt, undated. (Box 36, Folder 1)
- Photograph of Martha Zillhardt, undated. (Box 37, Folder 11)
- Photograph of Mr. Minton, Dick Edwards, N.W. Kelley, Irving Saks, W.P. Hunter, C.E. Hunter, Benton Dillard, and Mr. James, undated. (Box 35, Folder 10)
- Photograph of the National Capitol, undated. (Box 36, Folder 2)
- Photograph of Paul Getty, Jr., 1943. (Box 19, Folder 6)
- Photograph of Roanoke Airport, circa 1940. (Box 35, Folder 11)
- Photographs of Roselle Grubin, 2010 and undated. (Box 20, Folder 1)
- Photograph of Students of Woodrum Flying School, undated. (Box 35, Folder 13)
- Photograph of Train Accident, undated. (Box 35, Folder 1)
- Photographs of Unidentified Children, 1937-1989. (Box 20, Folder 2)
- Photographs of Unidentified Children, undated. (Box 20, Folder 3)
- Photographs of Unidentified Groups, 1944-1987. (Box 20, Folder 4)
- Photographs of Unidentified Groups, undated. (Box 20, Folder 5)
- Photographs of Unidentified Groups, undated. (Box 20, Folder 6)
- Photographs of Unidentified Groups, undated. (Box 20, Folder 7)
- Photographs of Unidentified Groups, undated. (Box 20, Folder 8)
- Photographs of Unidentified Groups, undated. (Box 21, Folder 1)
- Photographs of Unidentified Groups, undated. (Box 21, Folder 2)
- Photographs of Unidentified Groups, undated. (Box 21, Folder 3)
- Photographs of Unidentified Groups, undated. (Box 21, Folder 4)
- Photographs of Unidentified Groups, undated. (Box 21, Folder 5)
- Photographs of Unidentified Groups, undated. (Box 21, Folder 6)
- Photographs of Unidentified Groups, undated. (Box 21, Folder 7)
- Photographs of Unidentified Men, 1934-1943. (Box 22, Folder 1)
- Photographs of Unidentified Men, undated. (Box 22, Folder 2)
- Photographs of Unidentified Men, undated. (Box 22, Folder 3)
- Photographs of Unidentified Men, undated. (Box 22, Folder 4)
- Photographs of Unidentified Men, undated. (Box 22, Folder 5)
- Photographs of Unidentified Men, undated. (Box 22, Folder 6)
- Photographs of Unidentified Men, undated. (Box 22, Folder 7)
- Photographs of Unidentified Men, undated. (Box 22, Folder 8)
- Photographs of Unidentified Men, undated. (Box 23, Folder 1)
- Photographs of Unidentified Men, undated. (Box 23, Folder 2)
- Photographs of Unidentified Men, undated. (Box 23, Folder 3)
- Photographs of Unidentified Men, undated. (Box 23, Folder 4)
- Photographs of Unidentified Men, undated. (Box 35, Folder 12)
- Photographs of Unidentified Women, 1935 and undated. (Box 23, Folder 5)
- Photographs of Unidentified Women, 1935-1950 and undated. (Box 23, Folder 6)
- Photographs of Unidentified Women, 1957-1985 and undated. (Box 23, Folder 7)
- Photographs of Unidentified Women, undated. (Box 24, Folder 1)
- Photographs of Unidentified Women, undated. (Box 24, Folder 2)
- Photographs of Unidentified Women, undated. (Box 24, Folder 3)
- Photographs of Unidentified Women, undated. (Box 24, Folder 4)
- Photographs of Unidentified Women, undated. (Box 24, Folder 5)
- Photographs of Vehicles, 1937-1971 and undated. (Box 24, Folder 6)
- Photographs of Vehicles, 1974-1992 and undated. (Box 24, Folder 7)
- Pilot Flight Log, 1942-1949. (Box 25, Folder 1)
- Pilot Flight Log Book, 1942-1945. (Box 25, Folder 2)
- Pilot Log, 1944-1945. (Box 25, Folder 3)
- Pilot Log, undated. (Box 25, Folder 4)
- Pins, undated. (Box 29)
- Pocket Watch, undated. (Box 34, Folder 2)
- Poker Chips, undated. (Box 34, Folder 1)
- Price Family History, by J. Montgomery Seaver, 1929. (Box 25, Folder 5)
- Princess Patter Newsletter, 1976. (Box 25, Folder 6)
- Programs, 1928-1931. (Box 25, Folder 7)
- Programs, 1932-1959 and undated. (Box 25, Folder 8)
- Programs, 1974-1993. (Box 25, Folder 9)
- Proposed Sailings of U.S. Army Transports, 1938. (Box 25, Folder 10)
- Quartermaster Corps Transport Republic Menus, 1938. (Box 25, Folder 11)
- Quiet Birdman Newspaper, 1976. (Box 37, Folder 6)
- Real Estate Appraisal Report, 1953. (Box 25, Folder 12)
- Roanoke Assembly List of Members, undated. (Box 25, Folder 13)
- Scrapbook, 1938. (Box 26, Folder 1)
- Scrapbook (blank), undated. (Box 26, Folder 2)
- Scrapbook Page, undated. (Box 37, Folder 9)
- Scrapbook Pages, 1926-1929. (Box 26, Folder 4)
- Scrapbook, undated. (Box 27, Folder 1)
- A Sitka Welcome Newsletter, 1976-1977. (Box 27, Folder 2)
- S.S. Constitution List of Passengers, 1957. (Box 27, Folder 3)
- The Story of the Declaration of Independence, 1926. (Box 27, Folder 4)
- Tickets, 1930, 1932, 1974, and undated. (Box 27, Folder 5)
- The Virginia Realtor, September 1926. (Box 27, Folder 6)
- Wedding Album of Martha Price and Harry Hancock, 1951. (Box 27, Folder 7)
- Wedding Book of Martha Price Hancock, 1951. (Box 27, Folder 8)
- "Welcome to Woodrum Field", undated. (Box 37, Folder 12)
- Westport Women's Club Membership List, 1991-1992. (Box 27, Folder 9)
- Woodrum, Roosevelt, and the New Deal, by David J. Laing, 1981. (Box 27, Folder 10)
- Writings, undated. (Box 27, Folder 11)